A Guide to the Herschel Gustave Anderson Elarth Papers, 1885-1988
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Herschel Gustave Anderson Elarth Papers, 1885-1988
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1984-182
11.6 cu. ft. 7 boxes, 1 oversize folder
Papers of Herschel G. A. Elarth, professor of architecture, including correspondence, subject files, class materials, photographs, printed materials, artwork, scrapbooks, and ephemera chronicling Elarth's personal life, teaching and military careers, private practice, and participation in various architectural organizations.
Elarth, Herschel Gustave Anderson, 1907-1988
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Herschel Gustave Anderson Elarth Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1988.
Biographical Note
Herschel Gustave Anderson Elarth, son of Gustave and Amanda Anderson Elarth, was born in Omaha, Nebraska on October 15, 1907. Elarth attended the University of Illinois, earning a bachelor's degree in architecture in 1929. That same year, he submitted an entry for the Prix de Rome in architecture and was awarded first alternate. While attending college, Elarth also apprenticed with Omaha architect Thomas R. Kimball. Continuing his studies at the University of Illinois, Elarth earned a master of science in architecture in 1930, and in 1931, he took second place in the Society of Beaux Arts Architects' Paris Prize.
From 1931 to 1936, Elarth worked as an architectural designer in the Omaha firm of John and Alan MacDonald, playing a significant role in the final design of the Joslyn Art Museum. Moving to Los Angeles in 1937, Elarth worked for a year as a draftsman in the office of architect Richard J. Neutra. In January, 1938, Elarth took a position as professor of architecture at the University of Oklahoma. He married Wilhelmina van Ingen (1905-1969) in Norman, Oklahoma on April 2, 1942.
Elarth joined the U. S. Army in November, 1942. A first lieutenant, he served with the 826th Engineer Aviation Battalion, supervising the construction and maintenance of airfields. Following his honorable discharge in March, 1946, he took special studies at Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
During the summer of 1947, Elarth worked for two months as an architect for the Los Angeles City Planning Commission before being hired as an associate professor of architecture at the University of Manitoba. While there, he served as a consultant to the Winnipeg Town Planning Commission and designed the university's bus terminal and bookstore. He also designed the Fort Garry home in which the Elarths would live while in Manitoba.
In 1954, Elarth was hired as a professor of architecture at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. In addition to teaching and advising students, Elarth served as a member of the University Council, the VPI Self-Study and University Library Committee, the Judicial Committee, and the Wine Awards Committee. He also provided design consultation on what would eventually become Cowgill Hall. Early in his career at Virginia Tech, Elarth entered into a partnership with fellow architectural professor Charles S. Worley Jr., and among the projects they designed were the Montgomery County Public Health Center in Christiansburg and the Elarth residence in Blacksburg. Throughout the 1970s, Elarth was active in several architectural organizations, and was particularly involved in the environmental efforts of the American Institute of Architects (AIA). His contributions to architecture were recognized when he was elected a Fellow in the AIA in 1978.
Elarth married Eva Robert Frook (1917-1984) in Blacksburg, Virginia, in 1971, and he retired from the university in 1977. He continued, however, to be active as professor emeritus and in several architectural organizations. In 1984, Elarth sold his Blacksburg home and moved to Warm Hearth Village retirement community, where he also served on the board of directors. Herschel Elarth died in 1988.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the papers of architect Herschel Gustave Anderson Elarth, a professor at University of Oklahoma (1938-1942), University of Manitoba (1947-1954), and Virginia Tech (1954-1977). The collection includes such materials as correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, artwork, printed materials, course materials, architectural drawings, and ephemera relating to Elarth's personal life, experiences in World War II with the 826th Engineer Aviation Battalion, teaching career, private practice, organizational activities, and awards and honors.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series:
Series I. Personal Papers, 1885-1987. In this series are such items as biographical and genealogical materials, legal and financial documents, personal correspondence, and family photos. The series also includes materials (documents, insignia, photographs, and scrapbooks) relating to Elarth's service in the 826th Engineer Aviation Battalion during World War II. A collection of Elarth's artwork, consisting largely of studies of scenes in Omaha, the surrounding area, the greater Midwest, and Europe, rendered in watercolor, chalk, and crayon, completes the series.
Series II. Correspondence / Subject Files, 1919-1987. A collection of files maintained by Elarth on various artists and architects--most of whom were Elarth's personal acquaintances--may be found in this series. The files contain such materials as correspondence, original artwork, personalized greeting cards created by artists, and printed materials. (Note: The file on Frank Lloyd Wright contains only printed materials.)
Series III. Professorial Career, 1938-1987. Elarth's teaching career at the University of Oklahoma, University of Manitoba, and Virginia Tech is chronicled in this series. Included are lecture background materials, class assignment handouts and records, student projects, and student correspondence. The series also contains materials relating to Elarth's non-teaching duties, particularly his participation in committees and campus / local planning studies.
Series IV. Private Practice, 1927-1987. This series contains materials relating to various projects designed by Elarth, both individually and in partnership with Charles S. Worley Jr. The series begins with files devoted to a mural designed by Elarth, several competitions for which he submitted entries, and two projects on which he worked during the Great Depression. Covered in greater detail are three projects: the University of Manitoba bus terminal / bookstore; the Elarth residences in Fort Garry, Manitoba, and Blacksburg, Virginia; and the Montgomery County Public Health Center. The series also contains materials relating to other projects on which Elarth provided consultation and concludes with Elarth's awards, honors, and drafting kit. Note: Except where otherwise identified, all files in this series relate to Virginia Tech.
Series V. Architectural Organizations, 1961-1988. The materials in this series relate to Elarth's participation in several architectural organizations. The bulk of the material is devoted to the American Institute of Architects--both at the national and state levels--and reflects Elarth's interest in environmental policy. The series includes such materials as correspondence, memoranda, reports, and printed material, much of it devoted to such topics as surface mining, water quality, acid rain, and deforestation. The series also contains materials relating to other AIA committees on which Elarth served. Files relating to Elarth's participation in the Society of Architectural Historians--particularly regarding various society-sponsored tours--may also be found in this series.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Elarth, Wilhelmina van Ingen. Papers, Ms1969-004. Finding aid available on the Virginia Heritage database.
Separated Materials
The following items were removed from the collection, to be added to the Rare Book Collection:
"The Blue Ridge Parkway studies: policy, development, environmental, visual." Blacksburg, VA: Omnibus Studio, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, [1984].
The Roanoke Fine Arts Center history, 1952-1977. Roanoke, VA: Roanoke Fine Arts Center, [1978].
Land, issues and problems. (nos. 45-46, 50, 55-56). Blacksburg, VA: Cooperative Extension Service, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 1979-1981.
Mt. San Angelo's artists: a touring exhibition of works from the collection of the Virginia Center for the Creative Arts: September, 1985 - August, 1986. [Sweet Briar, VA: Virginia Center for the Creative Arts, 1986].
Shippee, Elizabeth Wright. "On receipt of a Stephan Lochner Madonna." [S.l.: s.n., 1936?].
Taliesin: the Taliesin Fellowship publication (vol. 1, no. 2). Spring Green, WI: Taliesin Fellowship, 1941.
Taliesin square-paper (no. 6). Spring Green, WI: Taliesin Press, [1941].
Taliesin square-paper (no. 8). Spring Green, WI: Taliesin Press, [1945].
Taliesin square-paper (unnumbered). Spring Green, WI: Taliesin Press, [1941].
World's Columbian Exposition, 1893: official catalogue. Part X. Department K. Fine Arts. Chicago: W. B. Gonkey, 1893.
Index Terms
Occupations:
Architects
Subjects:
Faculty; University Archives; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Series I. Personal Papers, 1885-1987
  - Biographical material, 1925-[1984], n.d. (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Curricula vitae, 1954-1976, n.d. (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Personal financial and legal documents, 1916-1974, n.d. (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Personal correspondence - Outgoing, 1918-1981, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Personal correspondence - Incoming, 1929-1986, n.d. (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Elarth Christmas cards, 1950, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Scrapbook, 1929-1981, n.d. (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Scrapbook, 1967-1975, n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Elarth studio portraits, 1925-1937, n.d. (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Family studio portraits, 1885-ca. 1912, (see also Oversize Materials) (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Family snapshots, 1920-1950, n.d. (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Military: photographs, documents, and printed material, 1942-1947, n.d. (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Military: insignia, n.d. (Box-folder 1-13)
  - World War II scrapbook I, 1942-1946, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-14)
  - World War II scrapbook II, 1942-1946, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-15)
  - European travel, 1930-1961, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Virginia / North Carolina tourism brochures, 1955, n.d. (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Masonic regalia, n.d. (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Masonic printed material, n.d. (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Elarth paintings, 1917-1928, (see also Box 6) (Box-folder 1-20)
  - Elarth watercolor studies of Douglas Lake, Michigan, 1979, n.d., (See also Box 6) (Box-folder 1-21)
- Series II. Correspondence / Subject Files, 1919-1987
  - Botta, Mario, 1986 (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Bowman, Richard and Peggy, 1956-1986, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Kamphoefner, Henry, 1962-1978, n.d. (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Kimball, Thomas R. / Nebraska State Capitol Competition, 1919-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Kingman, Eugene, 1955, n.d. (Box-folder 1-26)
  - McCloy, William, 1953-1977, n.d. (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Neutra, Richard and Dion, 1937-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 1-28)
  - Neutra, Richard - Elarth donation of Neutra-designed chair to Art Institute of Chicago, 1986-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 1-29)
  - Tanabe, Takao, 1952-1958, n.d. (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Tashiro, Gener, 1973-1979, n.d. (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1940-1979, n.d., (see also Box 7) (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Other artists / architects - greeting cards, 1957-1959, n.d. (Box-folder 2-4)
    - Carter, Dean, n.d., (3 items)
    - Eckhardt, Ferdinand, n.d.
    - Gerson, Wolfgang, n.d., (2 items)
    - Hornbostel, Caleb, [1957-1959], (2 items)
    - Pienkowski, Joni, n.d., (2 items)
    - Russell, John, n.d.
    - Unidentified, n.d.
  - Other artists - artwork, 1917-1984, n.d., (see also Box 7) (Box-folder 2-5)
    - Capshaw, Elmer, n.d.
    - Conant, Kenneth, 1917
    - Gregory, Dorothy Lake, n.d., (2 items); (see also Box 7)
    - Kent, Norman, n.d.
    - Murray, Patricia, 1946
    - Randall, E., 1937
    - Unidentified artists, [1960?], n.d., (4 items)
      General note
      (see also Box 7)
  - Other artists - printed material, 1950-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 2-6)
- Series III. Professorial Career, 1938-1987
  Scope and Contents note
  (Note: Except where otherwise identified, all files in this series relate to Virginia Tech.)
  - University of Oklahoma, 1938-1942 (Box-folder 2-7)
  - University of Manitoba, 1947-1954, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 2-8)
  - University of Manitoba - architectural course assignments, 1947-1955, n.d. (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Architecture 401 - Introduction to Housing, 1965, n.d. (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Architecture 4040 - Professional Practice, 1975 (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Construction Management / Professional Practice, 1967-1976, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Architectural design courses, 1949-1968, n.d., (6 folders) (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Architectural course materials and records, 1960-1977, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Student projects, 1956-1964, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Fifth-year student projects - exhibition building, 1961, n.d. (Box-folder 2-16)
  - Descriptive Environmental Systems, 1972, n.d. (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Architecture students, 1959-1977, n.d. (Box-folder 2-18)
  - Appointment, tenure, and retirement, 1954-1977, n.d. (Box-folder 2-19)
  - Teaching award nominations, 1976-1981, n.d. (Box-folder 2-20)
  - Wine awards, 1976-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 2-21)
  - College of Architecture and Urban Studies Advistory Council trip to Germany, 1987, n.d. (Box-folder 2-22)
  - Cowgill Hall / Hancock Hall, 1965-1985, n.d. (Box-folder 2-23)
  - Montgomery County Hospital study, 1960, n.d. (Box-folder 2-24)
  - College of Architecture, 1954-1974, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 2-25)
  - College of Architecture and Urban Studies, 1975-1985, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Virginia Tech Study and Planning Committee, 1965-1967, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture, 1958-1959, n.d. (Box-folder 3-3)
- Series IV. Private Practice, 1927-1987
  - Buffalo Hunters mural (Omaha, Nebraska), n.d. (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Beaux-Arts Institute of Design, 1927-[1931] (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Prix de Rome competition, 1929-1930, n.d. (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Joslyn Art Museum (Omaha, Nebraska), 1955-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 3-7)
  - Paris Prize of 1931, 1931-1982, (see also Oversize Materials) (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Spear-O-Wigwam (Sheridan, Wyoming), 1933, n.d., (see also Box 7) (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Sioux City, Iowa bandshell / Civil Works Administration, 1934-1936, n.d. (Box-folder 3-10)
  - Oregon State Capitol competition, n.d. (Box-folder 3-11)
  - Armory (Omaha, Nebraska), 1942, n.d. (Box-folder 3-12)
  - Charles A. Clark residence (San Diego, California), 1942, n.d. (Box-folder 3-13)
  - San Diego City Planning Commission, 1947-1948, n.d. (Box-folder 3-14)
  - Elarth residence (Fort Garry, Manitoba), 1948-1955, n.d., (see also Box 7) (Box-folder 3-15)
  - University of Manitoba bus station and bookstore (Winnepeg, Manitoba), 1951, n.d. (Box-folder 3-16)
  - Northern Sales Building (Winnipeg, Manitoba), n.d. (Box-folder 3-17)
  - National Gallery competition, 1952, n.d. (Box-folder 3-18)
  - Elarth and Worley, 1956-1968, n.d., (see also Box 7) (Box-folder 3-19)
  - Elarth residence (Blacksburg, Virginia) - plans and instructions, 1955-1956, n.d., (see also Box 7) (Box-folder 3-20)
  - Elarth residence (Blacksburg, Virginia) - 1955-1962, n.d. (Box-folder 3-21)
  - Elarth residence (Blacksburg, Virginia) - printed material, 1950-1982, n.d. (Box-folder 3-22)
  - Techbuilt Homes, n.d. (Box-folder 3-23)
  - Montgomery County Public Health Center (Christiansburg, Virginia), 1957 (Box-folder 3-24)
  - Smithman's Clothing Store (Christiansburg, Virginia), n.d. (Box-folder 3-25)
  - Paul M. Derring YMCA Retreat Center (Claytor Lake, Virginia), 1959-1960, n.d., (see also Box 7) (Box-folder 3-26)
  - Boston City Hall competition, 1961-1962, n.d. (Box-folder 3-27)
  - Smithfield Plantation (Blacksburg, Virginia), 1959-1961, n.d. (Box-folder 3-28)
  - Franklin D. Roosevelt Memorial, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 3-29)
  - Curtis Roane residence (Blacksburg, Virginia), 1961, (see also Box 7) (Box-folder 3-30)
  - Omaha post office and library preservation, 1966-1973, n.d. (Box-folder 3-31)
  - Richmond City Hall preservation, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 3-32)
  - John Phelps Cottage (Douglas Lake, Michigan), 1979, n.d. (Box-folder 3-33)
  - Warm Hearth Village, 1981-1984, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 3-34)
  - Blacksburg in the Eighties (BITE), 1983, n.d. (Box-folder 3-35)
  - Blacksburg townscape, 1987, n.d. (Box-folder 3-36)
  - Professional correspondence, 1935-1968 (Box-folder 3-37)
  - American Institute of Architects fellowship, 1978-1979, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 3-38)
  - Awards and honors, 1955-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 3-39)
  - Professional certificates and ephemera, 1941-1953, n.d., (see also Box 7) (Box-folder 3-40)
  - Architectural photographs, 1952-1961, n.d. (Box-folder 3-41)
  - Drafting kit, n.d. (Box-folder 3-42)
- Series V. Architectural Organizations, 1961-1988
  - American Institute of Architects - College of Fellows, 1976-1984, n .d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 4-1)
  - American Institute of Architects - Committee on Design, 1972-1976, n.d., (4 folders) (Box-folder 4-2)
  - American Institute of Architects - Regional Development and Natural Resources Committee, 1980-1982, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 4-3)
  - American Institute of Architects - Regional Development and Natural Resources Committee, 1982-1984, n.d., (5 folders) (Box-folder 4-4)
  - American Institute of Architects - Regional Development and Natural Resources Committee, 1984-1986, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 4-5)
  - American Institute of Architects - Committee on Regional Development and Natural Resources - Design Commission, 1981-1987, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 4-6)
  - American Institute of Architects - Regional Development and Natural Resources Committee - ecological checklist for architects, 1973-1980, n.d. (Box-folder 4-7)
  - American Institute of Architects - Regional Development and Natural Resources Committee - Federal Lands Subcommittee, 1979-1983, n.d., (5 folders) (Box-folder 4-8)
  - American Institute of Architects - Regional Development and Natural Resources Committee - surface mining policy, 1977-1981, n.d. (Box-folder 4-9)
  - American Institute of Architects - Regional Development and Natural Resources Committee - Wilderness Subcommittee, 1981-1985, n.d. (Box-folder 4-10)
  - American Institute of Architects - Urban Design and Planning Committee, 1986-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 4-11)
  - American Institute of Architects - public policy directory, 1984 (Box-folder 4-12)
  - American Institute of Architects - public policy directory, 1986 (Box-folder 4-13)
  - American Institute of Architects - Fellowship Committee, 1978-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 5-1)
  - Virginia Society, American Institute of Architects, 1978-1981, n.d. (Box-folder 5-2)
  - Virginia Society, American Institute of Architects, 1981-1982, n.d. (Box-folder 5-3)
  - Virginia Society, American Institute of Architects, 1983-1987, n.d., (3 folders) (Box-folder 5-4)
  - Virginia Society, American Institute of Architects - Government Affairs Committee, 1974-1988, n.d. (Box-folder 5-5)
  - Virginia Society, American Institute of Architects - Honors Committee, 1980-1985, n.d. (Box-folder 5-6)
  - Virginia Society, American Institute of Architects - Land Use and Natural Resources Committee, 1972-1979, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 5-7)
  - Virginia Society, American Institute of Architects - Land Use Planning and Development Committee, 1979-1987, n.d., (5 folders) (Box-folder 5-8)
  - Virginia Society, American Institute of Architects - Natural and Built Environment Committee, 1974-1982, n.d., (5 folders) (Box-folder 5-9)
  - Society of Architectural Historians, 1970-1978, n.d. (Box-folder 5-10)
  - Society of Architectural Historians, 1977-1979, n.d. (Box-folder 5-11)
  - Society of Architectural Historians, 1978-1981, n.d. (Box-folder 5-12)
  - Society of Architectural Historians, 1980-1982, n.d. (Box-folder 5-13)
  - Society of Architectural Historians - tour of Greece, 1978 (Box-folder 5-14)
  - Virginia Foundation for Architectural Education, 1975-1983, n.d. (Box-folder 5-15)
  - "Developing the American City" - Yale School of Architecture Symposium, 1987, n.d. (Box-folder 5-16)
  - International Union of Architects - Sixth Congress, 1961, n.d., (2 folders) (Box-folder 5-17)
  - Roadless Area Review and Evaluation (RARE II), 1978, n.d. (Box-folder 5-18)
- Oversize Materials, 1895-1984
  - Watercolor and charcoal studies by Elarth, 1928-1981, n.d., (79 items) (Box 6)
  - Spear-O Wigwam (Sheridan, Wyoming) construction photo album, 1933, n .d. (Box 7)
  - Charles A. Clark residence (San Diego, California) - perspectives, n.d., (2 items) (Box 7)
  - Elarth residence (Fort Garry, Manitoba) - plan, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Curtis Roane residence (Blacksburg, Virginia) - plans, 1951, (5 items) (Box 7)
  - Elarth residence (Blacksburg, Virginia) - plans, n.d., (12 items) (Box 7)
  - W. B. Gross residence (Blacksburg, Virginia) - plans, 1955, (8 items) (Box 7)
  - Paul M. Derring YMCA Retreat Center (Claytor Lake, Virginia) - plans and perspective, n.d., (3 items) (Box 7)
  - House for Unitarian Fellowship (Blacksburg, Virginia) - plans, 1967, n.d., (2 items) (Box 7)
  - Certification from Massachusetts Board of Registration of Architects, 1941 (Box 7)
  - Unidentified coarse textile (Native American?) (47 x 74 inches), n.d. (Box 7)
  - Studio portrait of unidentified woman (illegible signature) - by Portraits Zographos, Athens, n.d.
  - Floyd E. Brewer - woodcut, n.d.
  - [WAH Curfman?] - "St. Paul Swede Hollow (watercolor), 1932
  - Allison Flynn [Patrick James Allison Flynn] - charcoal still life, 1930 (Box 7)
  - Dorothy Lake Gregory - Alice in Wonderland illustrations, n.d., (2 items)
  - William Howell Smith - "Composition" [woodcut], 1984
  - Clifford M. Ulp - charcoal portrait of Ethel Bell van Ingen, n.d. n.d. (Box 7)
  - Clifford M. Ulp - charcoal portrait [of Wilhelmina van Ingen?], [1910?]
  - Hendrik van Ingen artwork, 1895-1917, n.d., (3 items)
  - Frank Lloyd Wright - "First Floor Plan No. 6 Life House, $5,000 Income", n.d. (Box 7)
  - Paris Prize drawings by Elarth, [1931] (Oversize 1)